and uh i was just sitting here
asking my friends when did we start this
llama and somebody said
in october something like that
november 2010
well
uh 12 years ago
and uh
part of my idea with teaching the slum
room was that it would take 20 years
and
for me
if i can get an injection of alarm rim
every six months or eight months then
it keeps me on track
and uh so alarm rim is a very good
foundation for
your whole life
and if you have
a teacher who's crazy and wants to teach
it to you for 20 years
and if you're both about the same age
then it'll probably work
and uh
and i think it's a great comfort for me
i i had this loan room
for 30 years from my teacher
and it was a great comfort to have it uh
a couple times a year and it kept me
grounded it kept me on track you know
and
if you i don't know if it happens to you
but it happens to me that i i uh
i sit down to meditate i go through the
preliminaries and then i'm like
i don't know what to do you know i don't
know what to meditate about sometimes i
i forget yeah i don't really have
something pressing to meditate
and then you can just go to the lung
room okay so if you get
an injection of lumram a couple times a
year
uh i think it's a wonderful thing
and and you always have something to
work on you always have something to
meditate on there's going to come a part
this time this session
where he says
a funny thing he says we've
we
we fear
lamrim meditations worse than death
and so i was like wow what's he what's
that
what's he trying to say you know
and he said
we all like the sexy
emptiness meditations or mahamudra
meditations or
we like to go to deeper meditations
and deeper books like
word smith's mind only book
we we like those deeper books you know
and then somebody says well why don't
you do some
ramen am i pausing for translation tim
deep breath i i could feel the tension
uh
[Music]
yeah uh
yeah if you
we tend to think oh i i'm i'd like to
focus on those really deep meditations
that we're getting in the mixed nuts or
something like that
uh but every every month or so go back
to the alarm room
and go back to where you are in the loan
room and uh you certainly have a
a steady stream of alarm rim for the
last uh how many years to 12 years
yeah and we'll be going for another 10
years or some
inshallah
so uh
so you know go back and and touch
touchstone use alarm rim as a touchstone
and it'll always ground you
it'll always give you a guide for the
rest for your life
it'll always
give you some kind of
orientation for your whole life and
you'll have structure for your whole
life a spiritual
structure for your whole life so i
really encourage you to
just check in with aluminum i i guess
we'll do it twice a year i've been doing
special programs
like medicine buddha and what's that
other one
nagarjuna
and we'll keep doing that uh
but i'll i'll keep forcing it back to
long run you know the students are all
like we want more emptiness uh we want
more tantra with medicine buddha and
i'm going to force it back to uh long
room
a couple times a year okay so
here we go
uh
this is a record
of a teaching
on the steps of the path to
enlightenment uh by kev j pabonko
rinpoche
and he was the teacher
of my teacher
and the teacher of my teacher's teacher
so my teacher's teacher was chija
rinpoche
who's the
junior tutor of his holiness and dilemma
and
he
was the greatest
teacher of his time
and his teacher was the greatest teacher
of his time
uh and then trija rinpoche
uh i don't i don't remember how old he
was at this time he was uh
he was in his 20s
and he did the transcription
of this 24 days of talks
24 days of public talks and he he wrote
it out and it took him about over 10
years to and he perfected the
the tibetan the tibetan is the i would
say it's the best book ever written in
tibetan
and uh now that tibetan is uh being lost
the language is being lost
probably it's the greatest book that
will ever be written in tibetan
so tonka of course is a great master but
this particular
book
linguistically is the greatest example
of tibetan ever written i think
and someone once asked me what was the
greatest book i ever read and i said
this
you know this is the most helpful book i
ever read
and i'm a book addict and my wife
accuses me of that
she said if it was between me and your
books i'm not sure which one you would
choose
and uh
but i love books and i've and i've read
you know
many
probably a couple thousand men
in tibetan and this is the greatest
uh
when we started 12 years ago
uh i taught the last two sections first
uh which was shamatha and vipassiana so
we
we did it backwards we went first
through
how to meditate
and then we went through emptiness
and then we went back to the beginning
of the book
and the the purpose of that was that
classically
you're supposed to meditate on these
topics as you go through them so this is
supposed to be
an yamcha which means experiential
teaching you're supposed to
uh learn the topic
and then go to diamond mountain retreat
center the best one in the universe
and don't hit my bald head
uh
and you're supposed to meditate on it
yeah you're supposed to go to your
retreat cabin and meditate on it and
we felt that uh when we were
preparing
this retreat a few months ago
it looked like the world wasn't quite
ready with the virus yet
and but i think
like in our state they dropped all
restrictions uh two days ago
and i think uh
i think we'll be back
uh for regular retreats unless something
weird happens
uh
what's the next one too
[Music]
in the fall
october yeah we'll be back here
you're very welcome to come
if they put you in quarantine you can do
that here also
and uh you just have a longer retreat so
uh
i
as far i think tim and and the whole
stuff uh venerable cinema we would like
to
to open it up again uh in the fall uh
so we did shamathan with asiana and then
we went back to
the
normal alarm room
and the goal there's an interesting
thing about this
which is a presentation of all the steps
to enlightenment
uh
the part about meditation and emptiness
is relatively short
and the reason i'm sure is that
in songkapa's
thousand page
great book on the steps of the past
half of it is devoted to emptiness
500 pages are roughly devoted to
emptiness and uh meditation
so i thought it'd be sexy to do the
short
meditation and emptiness from this one
first
then go through the whole alarm room and
then
go do the long run of songkapa which
would take
six or seven years or something
so uh that's the master plan
and uh we're on schedule we're doing
fine
we are about eighty percent done
with the first book uh so we're doing
well i think within two years we can
finish the first book
and then we'll switch over to songkapa
and that's gonna be
a lot okay
yeah uh that'll be
[Music]
220 pages from some couple which is 440
which is
uh we do about eight pages a day so call
it uh sorry eight pages of session
so that's 50 sessions
something like that
okay
so pray for a long life okay
all right
this first class
and tim i should stop at 10 to 7 right
or yeah
okay
uh am i supposed to do q a no later we
did that later
all right good
uh i thought the first class who i would
catch you up to where we are because uh
i forget everything where we are between
sessions and
i suppose you do too
so here's uh where we are okay there are
three great sections to the alarm room
uh first queue
which means people of lower capacity
medium capacity and higher capacity
and the teachings on people for lower
capacity
mainly are meant to keep you out of the
lower realms so after you pass away not
to go to the hell realms and animal
realms
uh the preto realms
and
we we finished that section
uh the second great section keyboard
ding is how to
stay out of sansara in general so even a
human rebirth even a daily rebirth
uh is so full of suffering
that uh an inevitable suffering you know
you don't have to have a war to kill
people
they kill themselves quite well
so the body
kills itself
uh you don't have to be in a car
accident or you will get old and you'll
fall apart and
it's a lot of fun
i i spent two days at doctors uh
the last two days and they
they're poking prodding you know
this is just maintenance like i'm really
careful
to uh
do my maintenance you know and and i i
really do go twice a year
they do everything
and you know
even if you do your maintenance you do
your yoga
you do your exercise
and i'm good at that and i eat fairly
carefully and
still is going to fall apart
so you just have to uh
that's the kind of suffering and this
the middle section of the alarm room
is to go beyond that suffering because
inevitably you will fall apart you can
you can exercise you can eat well uh
you can go to the doctors for
maintenance
mileage checkups
but it's there's only so much you can do
it's still going to fall apart
okay
so we've reached the third
grade section of the alarm room cable
chamber
which means i would like to
meet
all the people in this universe directly
one by one
and
human or otherwise
and i would like to commit
to serve them and help them
and
in time i would like to learn how to
save them
teach them
the alarm room teach them to get out of
this kind of body in this kind of
existence you know i
i would like to
to do that and it's a
a grand
motivation and you should go back to it
once in a while
and a real experience of bodhichitta
if you're an arya is that you
actually
meet each living being in the universe
even before you become enlightened and
you meet each one directly
and you have a few minutes with them and
you
commit to help them
uh and it's very touching right of
course
you know all the fish all the birds all
the viruses i guess
uh
you meet each one
and you kind of have a strong connection
with them you make a strong connection
with them
and you make a commitment to them
and that's a wonderful experience like
that itself if that's the only thing you
did with the whole alumni
in your life that would be
you can't imagine how that would change
your life or how that would change your
motivations or how that would change
your feeling about yourself
or your feeling about what i have to do
in this world
if you had that experience
i call it planet jumping
you kind of
go to every the planets are infinite
the beings are internet
in theory if they're coming from you
you can still meet each one
and you can finish them and come back
uh
if they're coming from you you can meet
them all and and you do
and it's it's quite a
game changer right changes your whole
life
and then you can't really be sad or
you can have bad days uh like the coffee
can be cold
it's not by the way
uh
you can have bad days and you can have
sad days but you can't really have a
terrible day
because you had this experience and so
i strongly
uh
urge you to try to have that experience
and the teaching this time
is about how to do that
so coincidentally
you're here for the big one
and this particular uh
session these how many days eight days
or something
uh
it's all seven days it's all focused on
uh having that experience
how do you trigger
that experience and
and wouldn't that be wonderful i mean
wouldn't that be the best thing that
ever happened to you and and there isn't
probably nothing sweeter than that than
to see it except for seeing emptiness
directly but you can do them at the same
time
almost so
here's a review of where we are
in the task
of trying to have that direct experience
of bodhichitta you can have other
experiences of bodhichitta
earlier
but they are more intellectual or
or or like that they're not the real one
okay uh we're called they're called
sugar cane
which means approximate
you get the taste of the outside of the
sugar cane the
what you call the peel you taste the
peel but not the center okay
all right
so we're gonna i'm gonna sort of start
reading
uh a little bit of a review okay symbol
cable chamber longinum
so this uh
third grade section of the alarm rim
that we're in
i will slow down transfers
uh
which is about uh
the path the steps on the path for those
people who choose to
to work for all living things
take change you
we went through sections where we said
the only way to
enter
that level
is to is to get bodhichitta and we'll
talk about bodhichitta we'll talk about
what it means okay
hang in there opinion means uh
specific benefits things that were cool
things that will happen to you
if you do have this experience
or other cool things that will happen to
you
and then we're going to have a section
on
how to make it happen so it's a typical
car salesman thing
they tell you how great the car is
and then they tell you how you can buy
it
i've been trying to buy a car for
veronica and uh
oh my god the whole thing switched
the
car salesman used to beg you to
they used to kiss your feed and it went
better from there
and now they're like what do you want
and i'm like new cars
forget it go home
you know i'll let you know
if there's a car you know
it's a it's unbelievable for a person
who
who's lived for this many years in this
world
it used to be the only people who
respected everybody was the car salesman
but that's forget that
[Music]
you're like give me a thousand bucks
i might keep a car for you
[Music]
anyway
we're doing a sales job here also okay
first we tell you how beautiful the car
is
like hey you could jump from planet to
planet
and
then we tell you how to get the car
[Music]
we might make it on the 31st of march
we might deliver it in two to three
weeks oh four to six weeks or maybe not
at all
that's how it that's how it went that's
the really hot one
and it's a weird color but it's the only
one available in northern arizona okay
uh
and then
once you have that experience
and you commit yourself to
taking care of each of those beings you
met which is the deal you made with them
when you met them
and i don't know why it's just a natural
thing when you meet them
you make a deal with each one
and you say don't worry i'm on it i'm
taking care of it you know it's like tim
takes care of the lumbering stuff
and uh
and so how do you carry out that deal
how do you keep your
your part of the agreement
and that's the six perfections
so we'll get to those later
but we're not quite done with
how to get bodhichitta
[Music]
by the way bodhichitta has been
translated as enlightenment mind it's a
bad translation as so many translations
are
it just means
the wish to get enlightened to help
other people that's all it doesn't have
to do with being enlightened you're not
enlightened
you're committing to get enlightened so
it cannot be enlightened it's a bad
translation
all right uh the first section as i said
was the sales job
and i thought i would go through the
sales job as a review okay so we'll just
take a few minutes
and we'll go through the sales jump okay
uh
juice is
here's a famous verse
about
the cool things that are going to happen
to you
if you can get to bodhichitta okay
here's a famous sales
pitch
about your new car your car's working
okay right so far
wait till you hit a rocket down okay
all right
uh tim first image
if you can
yeah
uh
you are beloved and protected so i i i'm
gonna give you about
uh
150 images
uh we call them idea images in them
and
can you guys see them
yeah
uh
i i give you these images as a
self-testing
method okay so
between the end of class today and the
beginning of class tomorrow
you should be able to look
at it's going to be about
eight to ten images for this whole class
and i want you to be able to self-test
yourself
and that's a nice way to review okay you
don't have to remember all the details
just remember the picture okay
if you remember what the picture's about
then you succeeded in your review
and you should you should look at the
pictures by tomorrow okay again at home
uh let's bring it up again tim
if you i know you're having a
okay good
uh this is the first
advertised
benefit of getting to bodhichitta and
it's that you will be beloved and
protected by enlightened beings okay
well gesh love
i'm already beloved and protected by
enlightened beasts yeah but especially
be loving and pretending okay
so if you made this commitment to
helpful beings
then uh
your dad and mom which is all the
buddhas of the universe
of course they have equal love for all
beings but they feel special about you
because you're kind of like the good
daughter or the good son
who's gonna help the family help carry
on the family so they
they feel especially close to you
that's the
first one uh
and
uh other other beings and they list
specifically uh powerful
spirit beings and even other human
beings
will be
uh
they'll be attracted to helping you
achieve your goals uh and they don't
know why
like the people around you will
will
smell something about you
uh i did take a shower this morning
but they will smell it's cold in 4 30
anyway
uh you will
people can sense
what you're up to
okay they don't know directly they don't
know you they they don't know what
you're doing they meet you in the
grocery store
and they get a feeling about you and
they serve you and they help you
do the things you want to do to help
people so it's a nice feeling
you feel very protected and you feel
very nurtured
by other people because they are they
smell something about your ultimate
goals
and they want to help you and it's a
it's a nice experience it's people are
constantly
uh trying to help you get things done
and do what you have to do and uh
throwing money at you to do your
projects it's weird
and they sense that something's going on
and and so it's a very beautiful uh
feeling of being supported okay so
that's the first selling point
in general you will get a lot of support
from the universe
uh because of what you're trying to do
and the universe will know even if they
don't know exactly what's going on okay
even people you never met will
will take care of you and they will
someone means
they will
protect you from negative
events negative people negative
experiences people will be constantly
trying to
[Music]
make sure that nothing happens to you
and it's a nice feeling and
it kind of if you're on this mission
to help all living beings you attract
support and you attract
protect
protection
okay just automatically and your life is
pretty cool
all right uh second picture here
yeah i you know and i have this uh
photo
stock photo agency called one two three
rf i don't get a commission
uh
i pay them 158 dollars a month just
because i i love their pictures they're
always positive
uh they're always friendly this
particular
the second benefit
of
of getting bodhichitta or trying to get
bodhichitta is that you'll just be happy
all the time
so you always
be it doesn't mean you can't be grumpy
if you have to get up
early i got it tim
uh
you could still be grumpy in the morning
at diamond mountain but uh
in general
you feel really happy
and uh
you notice it you know like your friends
are all having a bad day and you're and
they're like
i'm having a bad day and you're like
yeah i know
you know
[Music]
and uh
and they sometimes they get mad at you
you know why are you always having a
good day you know i don't know
so uh
in general your life will be
uh blessed you feel happy most of the
time you feel
deeply happy
you're in a good mood all the time even
when stuff is going wrong you know
the county doesn't give your cafe a
permit for eight months
for a small toilet
then you're like okay
[Music]
you know okay so
and also physically you'll feel as much
as the human body allows you will feel
healthy and strong
bodies in
you know a pretty good condition after
70 years
you will feel generally quite good most
of the time
that's a second it's a side effect of uh
body children it's not the main goal
but
it happens and it's noticeable
all right uh so now you got two pictures
don't forget what they are
and
you can test yourself and you can also
use these
images for your meditations each day
so when you go home from this class
take a long nap
unless your staff right so i said then
you have to work hard
then taking that
during the tomorrow's class
but uh
take a long nap and then
do some meditations and do some light
meditations you could also uh
i write down the the the names of the
images and i go for an hour walk here at
diamond beautiful
it's a great place to walk so just take
it with you and say what was
what was that all about the the picture
of the lady with the smile
you know and self-test yourself every
day and then it will stick the teaching
will stick if you don't you'll just
it'll all be a blur and you won't
remember anything by the end okay
all right uh
third
fourth
third image
really
why do i have for you
you're protected
you feel joyful
oh yeah okay i like this one
uh
stuff cannot hurt you
all right
you ready tim
we got sharks
yeah i like this picture
uh
you know all the problems in your life
are waiting down there
and you're just walking through them you
know and uh
that's the
third group of
benefits
selling points
for bodhisattva
is that uh
yes there will be problems around you
there will be wars and there will be
viruses and
and there will be economic problems
and just somehow it always just skips
you
okay and you just float on
uh
and that's kind of
that's kind of cool you're always in the
wrong place at the right time for
problems
and uh they just kind of miss you you
know and your friends are having
problems and your other friends are
having problems and
and you feel kind of guilty that you
don't have them
and you're god i wish someone would
attack my country
and um
you know you just feel kind of
if i feel sometimes guilty that i'm not
having worse problems
but but if you
have this motivation
uh problems will just generally skip you
and stuff that have like uh
i did get covered finally
uh just before the mixed nut last mix
nuts term and i was desperate because i
didn't have time to prepare 60 classes
which takes 240 hours to prepare
and
and i was desperate and
then i got a coping
and i was three blissful days in bed
and i was just veronica came in she said
what are you what are you working on
for 12 hours a day you know i'm like i
like catching up with the mixed nuts you
know
this cobia thing is so great
and uh
it was just three very relaxing days in
bed
and i had my computer on my chest and
then
you know doing all these classics and
so even if you get a problem it's not
really a problem and it just comes at
the right time
okay so uh
that's another benefit of this
bodhichitta okay uh
problems happen around you people are
getting common
people are dying
and you're having a blissful three days
and good
uh pretend protecting
preparing your next class you know
and
nothing really
goes really wrong in your life okay
okay
next picture uh
yeah she's i i i saw this picture i
thought this is good you will accomplish
all your goals okay things you want to
do
will work out okay and i think before
you get bodhichitta
you try to do things you try to do
projects
and they don't quite work out
or things
get stalled they get delayed
things don't happen
and if you
are able to get bodhichitta
then all the projects you're doing uh
against all odds they succeed
you know people show up
to build the university in kyoto
right
and pay for it and and just things
happen
and
projects that you start goals that you
have personal goals that you have
uh it says here pepa memphis
means uh
you don't have to try that hard just
things click
and people show up
i gotta tell you a cute story i can talk
about that probably
[Music]
this is called dharma bragging which i'm
an expert at uh so uh
i was trying to raise money for two new
translators for the mixed nuts
and it's expensive these guys are
expensive they keep having babies
and
uh
so
so i i
i had to raise uh
some money for these
translators two new translators need
salary
it's a lot of money
and uh i was like god i don't know how
i'm gonna do this but i just trust and i
i was whining about two of my friends
bought teslas recently
right
stanley and uh
seiji
and i i was whining about they have this
god you get in the car
and you just like go like this and the
car drives down the street really fast
and everyone's like
you know
and
i'm like
those two friends got these teslas and
i'm stuck with this old toyota
and uh
so one of the people listening to the
broadcast
sent me a message
and they said i'll buy you any tesla you
want
you know tomorrow
and i'm like
then i researched what's the most
expensive one you know
it's
157 000 or something
so i'm like
okay i need that one you know
and this person is like okay you got it
and uh then i said you know but my car
works okay
uh you donate the money for these two
salaries
same money same exact dollars you know
and they're like
okay and
so what i mean is that stuff just works
out
stuff just keeps working out and we got
the salaries for the two translators
even though another translator got
pregnant last week
i don't know if i'm supposed to say who
it was
you'll figure it out
he's gonna need all the money he wins
in my classes
constantly
okay
i hope he doesn't get mad at me
uh
yeah so stuff you want to achieve will
just happen okay stuff will
cool stuff will happen projects that you
trying to do they will work out okay and
that's all the blessing of this out of
this motivation
to help all the beings in the
universe okay
so those are three how many did we have
in general
uh you will be protected and and beloved
what's the picture
yeah the baby yeah
you will feel joy
that happy lady
uh
nothing can touch you
yeah the sharks like bad stuff can't
touch you okay
it bad stuff happens
around you but it never quite affects
you
you know uh
and then fourthly what
yeah you achieve the things you want so
you just have four pictures to remember
this whole class
okay just remember four pictures and
when you're meditating
uh
try to you know your eyes are closed and
you're like what's the next picture he
showed
what was the next picture and the the
picture is a mnemonic to trigger the
to trigger the memory of of these
benefits about each other okay so four
right
four pictures four main groups of
benefits
will happen to you first one
protected and beloved second one
sleeping
what
happy third one
sharks
fourth one
yeah just stuff happens
you get the tesla money for translators
okay
all right
[Music]
then uh after selling us
on bodhichitta
uh they gave us
several
they listed the ways to get body chin
okay so they sold they did a sales job
oh you need a now i know all the suvs in
the universe
i spent like weeks meditating on all the
suvs in the universe
so they're like okay i want the
rav4 or the subaru forester
and then
okay you got it clear what you want yeah
okay now how do you get it
how that's the second big category how
do you get
how do you get this body cheated that is
so cool okay that the salesman sold you
on the salesman
[Music]
two
generally two different methods
of achieving uh bodhichitta two
different methods of getting one okay
and uh
generally the first one is going to be
chung chuk to sam john remember
these are the steps
to developing
that breakthrough
okay the steps that you have to go
through
to have that breakthrough where you're
jumping planet the planet which is
really sexy
like it's worth a couple months of work
to
jump planet
i i don't like this body to the word
that much
i just jumping from planet to planet
stopping off on each planet
checking in with everybody
ah don't worry i'm taking care of you
i'm on it they jump to the next planet
so um
and by the way the more you uh
study emptiness the more you know that's
possible okay it's not some kind of uh
exaggeration
uh if if the pen is coming from you
then planet jumping is feasible
then planet jumping is possible okay
so we're gonna study the ways to
actually
get the
and then we're gonna
have uh
a formal
ceremony
for committing to the
commitments of a bodhisattva okay so
there's two huge sections number one
how do you learn
planet jumping
and then number two
uh there's a beautiful ceremony
for committing to that way of life okay
and and generally when you teach
uh how to be a bodhisattva you cover it
in those two steps you
you talk about how to get the motivation
and then you
plan some kind of grand ceremony i
remember in new york city when we
started the aci courses uh
we we went through the vows
for months
and then we kept talking with each other
like wow let's have a really cool
ceremony we we rented the uh you were
you were there quaker church
we rented the quaker church we had the
classes there
uh
finally uh we had the ceremony it was
really fun
then the quaker church came and said you
can't come here anymore
and we're like why
what what'd we do wrong we we cleaned up
and everything and they said nah
it's that
people in this neighborhood are starting
to call this the buddhist church
so you can't come anymore
that's really sad
anyway we had fun
so to have a grand ceremony at some
point would be nice
and you can recommit if you already have
those spells you're allowed to re take
them you can't retake
nun spells you take them once that's it
that's the end of it you're stuck
but bodhisattva vowels you can keep
refreshing them
[Music]
all right
yeah and i have a picture here for you
and uh
she's just thinking of something okay
and
sometimes bodhichitta
is just called the thought
okay so i just want you to
think about uh the whole
practice of of trying to get bodhichitta
is
is in this picture it's not an activity
really it's a thought
it's an intention okay so
so when you see this picture
you're thinking oh
bodhichitta you know i would like to get
bodhichitta and she doesn't look
different
she's not obviously acting differently
it's a change in your outlook okay it's
a change in how you
it's a change in your intention for your
life and other people cannot really see
it it's just a it's just a
way of
looking okay and so
that's what this picture is supposed to
remind you of okay this picture is
supposed to remind you of
uh
bodhichitta is a
is an outlook that kind of looks to the
future she looks like she's stuck into
the future a little bit
right
and uh
and she looks like she has some cool
secret
uh
but it's a perfect picture for
bodhichitta okay
uh
and there's two options next picture tim
if you wanna get to bodhichitta
there's two
classic paths
there's two classic methods okay uh
one is called
uh
the
seven step cause and effect method
advice may not okay the seven step cause
and effect
advice
is
classical method
of reaching bodhichitta okay
and then the second
classical method is who can guess
say again
uh
maybe
oh that's another one ah
yeah exchange equal
you can say exchanging stuff in others
but it's really it's called equalizing
and exchanging equaling and exchanging
english word for the first one
it means recognizing the equal rights of
all living beings okay is the first half
of the second method the second method
starts with
recognizing the aid
of all living beings okay
the belief
that all living beings have equal rights
not just the black people white people
not just women and men
not just one country and another
all living beings have equal rights
and then the second part of that is
exchanging yourself and others which is
the famous part okay
and really that's always together and
it's always two parts
so
people have called it
exchanging self and others but it's
technically
it's
equal rights
and then exchanging and it always has
those two parts equal rights
and then exchanging and the exchanging
self of others is not what it sounds
like
that's a famous
warning
doesn't mean putting yourself in another
person's shoes it doesn't mean that it
has a deeper meaning
a deeper depressing meaning
okay which we study in this year
all right
uh i got two minutes right tim
one minute too tough hey i did it
perfect uh
so
we've been going through the seven step
cause and effect
method we've been working on that
and and we're up to the last one we did
six
we got one to go what are the six you
start with equanimity for everybody
then you
marshay
recognize that people have been your
mother 10-10
remember all the nice things they did
for you
chin soul
try to repay
jamba
love
and then ninja
yeah
how many is that
yeah i said
sometimes they don't count equanimity
so any
realize they've been your mother mache
remember what they did for you want to
pay them back
love them
and want to protect them from suffering
you can you can count uh equanimity
and then we've reached the number seven
okay
which is the result that's why it's
called the causa
cause and result instruction okay first
six are caused
seventh one is is bodhichitta so we've
actually reached the bodhichitta one we
did this
we did all those other steps and now
we've reached the result
which is the final part of the first
method okay cool
and in the next class
we'll be going on to
uh pavonkovich's description of
bolichima okay
and
and then we do one after that
breakfast
now then we'll go to the second method
for buddhism
which is
uh
equal rights and exchanging equal rights
and exchange okay good then we'll go to
the second method
by the way it is said traditionally
that the second method is more powerful
uh
they say if you could start with the
first method
and then add the second method that's an
unbeatable combination
okay
the second method on top of the first
method
is the ultimate method so it's good to
have
both and the second one supercharges the
first one
cool
all right we're going to take a 10
minute
old man pb break
and
we'll see you see you again right tim in
10 minutes okay so please have a nice
break and
see you then